"Use Fiber to Burn Calories in Your Sleep
with an Intestinal Workout"
Fiber can literally help
flush calories away,
assisting with
weight management.
A review entitled
"Food Fibre as an Obstacle
to Energy Intake"
summarized the four Ds
by which dietary fiber results
in reduced caloric intake.
There's the dilution of calories
by expanding the volume of food,
distention of the stomach
through fluid absorption,
delay in stomach emptying
of the gelled mass,
and dumping of calories
by blocking the absorption
of other macronutrients.
That fourth D triggers
a fifth phenomenon,
known as the ileal brake.
As Dr. Greger has covered,
the ileum is the last part
of the small intestine
before it empties
into the colon.
When undigested nutrients
are detected that far down,
the body puts the brakes
on further eating
by curbing our appetite.
So, there are lots of ways
eating more fiber can help
with weight regulation.
Across more
than 10 weight-loss studies,
those randomized to consume
higher-fiber diets
lost more weight,
even when calorie intake
was fixed.
So, more weight loss,
even when prescribed
the same number of calories.
If it wasn't the "calories in"
side of the equation,
was it the "calories out"?
Normally that means things
like exercise,
but in the case
of high-fiber diets,
there literally
are calories out,
as in out the other end
and flushed down the toilet.
But the same-calorie,
higher-fiber groups
were losing more weight
than could be accounted for,
even after taking into account
the excess calorie dumping.
Where were the calories going?
To solve the mystery
of the missing calories,
researchers fed people
different amounts of fiber
and sealed them
in an airtight chamber
called a whole-body calorimeter
to closely monitor
their metabolic rate.
Those with more fiber
in their system
were burning more calories
even in their sleep!
Only about 2% more,
but that translated
into burning
almost 50 more calories a day
without getting off the couch.
For people on long-term
fiber-rich diets,
they figured that all that fiber
might bulk up
their intestinal lining,
which is a highly
metabolically-active tissue.
Why were they spontaneously
burning off more energy
even when they were asleep?
It turns out
all that extra fiber
may have been giving their gut
a workout.
Our intestines
are muscular tubes.
So, our small intestine is like
20 feet (6.10 m) of muscle,
which contracts in waves
to move food along.
But fiber-depleted foods
don't offer much resistance.
The apple juice
and Wonder Bread
get absorbed almost immediately
and don't put up
much resistance.
It's like weight lifting
with a barbell
made out of Styrofoam.
Not very effective.
Researchers had people swallow
long strings of electrodes
to measure
the electrical activity
of the muscular contractions
of the intestines
of those eating low-fiber meals
versus high-fiber meals.
The individuals
eating more fiber
not only had stronger, faster,
longer contractions,
but reduced the periods
of intestinal inactivity.
Turns out our gut
can be sedentary, too.
But if we eat lots
of fiber-rich foods,
we can be asleep
and our gut will still
be exercising all night long.